Do you have anything in your home that you never use but can't bear to throw out? Maybe
some old toys from your childhood, or books that you never finished reading, or an outdated
cell phone that you think you might need in an emergency. Everyone hangs on to some items
longer than is necessary, but hoarders take this practice to the extreme.
Hoarding is a form of behavior which means that a person simply cannot part with anything.
It is more than just the desire to collect old things. Hoarders hold on to everything
they own forever, no matter how useless it may seem to others. Commonly hoarded items
include personal possessions like clothes and photographs, as well as more unusual things
such as buttons and old electronics. Some people even keep garbage like old newspapers
and advertisements. One woman reported needing 58 enormous boxes to carry useless art supplies
with her when she moved to a new house. But hoarding isn't just an unusual personal
characteristic. It can lead to serious consequences for people. For one thing, hoarders tend to
be very disorganized. Boxes and rooms fill up with trash, and this can lead to a dirty
and unhealthy living situation. Another problem is the emotional impact on the hoarder's
family. Imagine living with a family member who gets upset any time you try to throw something
away. It can be incredibly stressful for everyone involved. Hoarding is recognized as a psychological
problem, so it is possible for hoarders to get treatment. One woman participated in a
30-day program which encouraged her to throw out one item on the first day, two on the second day,
and so on. Throwing away your trash may seem simple and natural to most of us. For hoarders,
though, it can be a long and often painful road to cleaning up both their homes and their lives.